<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1 | Bonald Ziyue LI</title>
    <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication_types/1/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bonaldli.github.io/publication_types/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>1</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 15:01:26 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>1</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication_types/1/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>CoSLight: Co-optimizing Collaborator Selection and Decision-making to Enhance Traffic Signal Control</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/coslight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 15:01:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/coslight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What life mottos have we learned from traffic signal control? Wait! What?
Yes, we learned that &lt;strong&gt;“you are your biggest collaborator”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“Collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”&lt;/strong&gt; from the traffic light!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every driver would have realized that the traffic patterns in different regions (residential v.s. downtown) at different hours (midday v.s. evening peak) are quite different. The same should have been true of the traffic signal coordination! In our CoSLight, we co-optimize the collaborating policy ρ (choosing which traffic light as a collaborator) and the decision-making policy π (delivering which traffic control phase for the next timeslot). It turns out to be working very, Very, VERY well: our CoSLight can choose different sets of traffic lights for collaboration at different times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we also learned life philosophies from the traffic light agents, very (ironically) deep:
(1) When we drop the traffic light itself from being its own collaborator, the performance drops 2%: “You are your biggest collaborator”.
(2) When you collaborate with me, but I don&amp;rsquo;t collaborate with you, a.k.a, not being mutually reciprocal (mathematically not being symmetric), the performance drops 300%!!!: “Collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All right, “collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”: we learned the important lesson the hard way&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>X-Light: Cross-City Traffic Signal Control Using Transformer on Transformer as Meta Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learner</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/xlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 15:00:22 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/xlight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-Temporal Large Language Model for Traffic Prediction</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/stllm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 14:58:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/stllm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL-to-Schema Enhances Schema Linking in Text-to-SQL</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/schemalinkingsql/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 15:01:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/schemalinkingsql/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PDiT: Interleaving Perception and Decision-making Transformers for Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/pdit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 23:58:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/pdit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;: In PDiT, we proposed a Transformer-interleaving-Transformer architecture for specialized environment perception and decision-making: it is a multi-modal generalist agent for vision, language, and numerics!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DuaLight: Enhancing Traffic Signal Control by Leveraging Scenario-Specific and Scenario-Shared Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dualight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 18:30:13 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dualight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Neighbors Also Matter to Kriging: A New Contrastive-Prototypical Learning</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/kcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 14:59:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/kcp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Large Language Model-based Agents for Large-Scale Decision-Making: An Actor-Critic Approach</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/llm-actorcritic-naacl23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 23:47:28 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/llm-actorcritic-naacl23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TPTU-v2: Boosting Task Planning and Tool Usage of Large Language Model-based Agents in Real-world Systems</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tptu_v2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 23:51:41 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tptu_v2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Dirichlet Process Multinomial Mixture Model with Graphs for Passenger Trajectory Clustering</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tensordpmm-sigspatial23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 23:58:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tensordpmm-sigspatial23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Critical Perceptual Pre-trained Model for Complex Trajectory Recovery</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/co_paper_sensetime_rangatt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 16:08:37 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/co_paper_sensetime_rangatt/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KITS: Inductive Spatio-Temporal Kriging with Increment Training Strategy</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/kits-iclr24/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 00:06:12 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/kits-iclr24/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reboost Large Language Model-based Text-to-SQL, Text-to-Python, and Text-to-Function -- with Real Applications in Traffic Domain</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/reboost-icde24/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:08:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/reboost-icde24/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TPTU: Large Language Model-based AI Agents for Task Planning and Tool Usage</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tptu-icde24/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:12:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tptu-icde24/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Causal Graph Convolutional Network for Traffic Prediction</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dbgcn-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:27:59 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dbgcn-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correlated Time Series Self-Supervised Representation Learning via Spatiotemporal Bootstrapping</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/time-series-ssl-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:27:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/time-series-ssl-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Hierarchical SpatioTemporal Network for Traffic Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/adaptive-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:27:02 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/adaptive-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MM-DAG: Multi-task DAG Learning for Multi-modal Data--with Application for Traffic Congestion Analysis</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mmdag-kdd23/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:28:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mmdag-kdd23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Privacy-preserving Heart Rate Prediction System for Drivers in Connected Vehicles</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/heart-driving-mobi23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2023 00:28:56 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/heart-driving-mobi23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Probabilistic Framework for Spatiotemporal Passenger Crowdedness Inference within Urban Rail Transit Network</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mtr-crowd-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 00:27:27 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mtr-crowd-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jointly contrastive representation learning on road network and trajectory</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/co_paper_sensetime_roadgraph/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 16:08:37 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/co_paper_sensetime_roadgraph/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Topic Models with Graphs and Applications on Individualized Travel Patterns</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/icde2021-phdsym/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 18:20:55 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/icde2021-phdsym/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Completion for Weakly-dependent Data on Graph for Metro Passenger Flow Prediction</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/wdgtc-aaai20/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 16:32:57 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/wdgtc-aaai20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-medal&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Award:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is awarded with &lt;strong&gt;Best Student Paper Finalist Award&lt;/strong&gt; in INFORMS 2020 Quality, Statistics, and Reliability (QSR) Section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From our last paper, we found out low-rank tensor completion tends to ill-perform in heterogeneous stations. This is because LRTC assume a low rank structure in data, i.e. low-rank property implies that data in all stations are strongly and linearly dependent. However, two spatial correlations in station dimension are observed: only stations that are geographically close or functionally similar are more likely to have same passenger flow patterns. We offered a temporary solution by conducting LRTC within each station cluster to guarantee low-rank structure. But we would also like to look for a better solution, a low-rank tensor completion method that could directly handle the data with local spatial correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore we proposed a tensor completion method for Weakly-dependent Data on Graph (WDG). We formulate the geographical correlation and functional similarity as two graphs, and introduce them as two Laplacian regularizations into LRTC, namely, into station-feature matrix $\mathbf{U}^{station}$, such that if two stations are close on the two graphs, they have similar parameters on $\mathbf{U}^{station}$. Besides, since there are those two graphs on station dimension, if any 2 stations are randomly picked, they’re less likely to be highly-dependent if they’re not connected in either of two graphs. We formulate this weak dependency as a sparse coding via $l_1$-norm, such that a station is represented with only a small amount of highly-related stations as “basis”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are the first work to provide a Low Rank Tensor Completion solution to weakly-dependent pattern on graphs. And the completion result could achieve 40% higher accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
