<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tensor Decompositoin | Bonald Ziyue LI</title>
    <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/tensor-decompositoin/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/tensor-decompositoin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Tensor Decompositoin</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 16:32:57 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bonaldli.github.io/images/logo_hua8a87e19eb81e012a11357248f4216c8_33222_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Tensor Decompositoin</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/tensor-decompositoin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Completion for Weakly-dependent Data on Graph for Metro Passenger Flow Prediction</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/aaai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 16:32:57 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/aaai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-medal&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Award:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is awarded with &lt;strong&gt;Best Student Paper Finalist Award&lt;/strong&gt; in INFORMS 2020 Quality, Statistics, and Reliability (QSR) Section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From our last paper, we found out low-rank tensor completion tends to ill-perform in heterogeneous stations. This is because LRTC assume a low rank structure in data, i.e. low-rank property implies that data in all stations are strongly and linearly dependent. However, two spatial correlations in station dimension are observed: only stations that are geographically close or functionally similar are more likely to have same passenger flow patterns. We offered a temporary solution by conducting LRTC within each station cluster to guarantee low-rank structure. But we would also like to look for a better solution, a low-rank tensor completion method that could directly handle the data with local spatial correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore we proposed a tensor completion method for Weakly-dependent Data on Graph (WDG). We formulate the geographical correlation and functional similarity as two graphs, and introduce them as two Laplacian regularizations into LRTC, namely, into station-feature matrix $\mathbf{U}^{station}$, such that if two stations are close on the two graphs, they have similar parameters on $\mathbf{U}^{station}$. Besides, since there are those two graphs on station dimension, if any 2 stations are randomly picked, they’re less likely to be highly-dependent if they’re not connected in either of two graphs. We formulate this weak dependency as a sparse coding via $l_1$-norm, such that a station is represented with only a small amount of highly-related stations as “basis”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are the first work to provide a Low Rank Tensor Completion solution to weakly-dependent pattern on graphs. And the completion result could achieve 40% higher accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
