<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Traffic Management | Bonald Ziyue LI</title>
    <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/traffic-management/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/traffic-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Traffic Management</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 15:01:26 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Traffic Management</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/traffic-management/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>CoSLight: Co-optimizing Collaborator Selection and Decision-making to Enhance Traffic Signal Control</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/coslight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 15:01:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/coslight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What life mottos have we learned from traffic signal control? Wait! What?
Yes, we learned that &lt;strong&gt;“you are your biggest collaborator”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“Collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”&lt;/strong&gt; from the traffic light!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every driver would have realized that the traffic patterns in different regions (residential v.s. downtown) at different hours (midday v.s. evening peak) are quite different. The same should have been true of the traffic signal coordination! In our CoSLight, we co-optimize the collaborating policy ρ (choosing which traffic light as a collaborator) and the decision-making policy π (delivering which traffic control phase for the next timeslot). It turns out to be working very, Very, VERY well: our CoSLight can choose different sets of traffic lights for collaboration at different times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we also learned life philosophies from the traffic light agents, very (ironically) deep:
(1) When we drop the traffic light itself from being its own collaborator, the performance drops 2%: “You are your biggest collaborator”.
(2) When you collaborate with me, but I don&amp;rsquo;t collaborate with you, a.k.a, not being mutually reciprocal (mathematically not being symmetric), the performance drops 300%!!!: “Collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All right, “collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”: we learned the important lesson the hard way&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>X-Light: Cross-City Traffic Signal Control Using Transformer on Transformer as Meta Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learner</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/xlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 15:00:22 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/xlight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DuaLight: Enhancing Traffic Signal Control by Leveraging Scenario-Specific and Scenario-Shared Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dualight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 18:30:13 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dualight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MultiFun-DAG: Multivariate Functional Directed Acyclic Graph</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/multifundag/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 15:00:34 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/multifundag/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FELight: Fairness-Aware Traffic Signal Control Via Sample-Efficient Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/felight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 14:59:50 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/felight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL; DR&lt;/strong&gt;:  It&amp;rsquo;s traffic signal control again, but what&amp;rsquo;s new here? How can we ensure that the agents control the traffic light fairly? We embedded such fairness metrics into Reinforcement Learning models. Furthermore, how can we minimize the sample required and achieve a resource-efficient agent? We used self-supervised learning!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Causal Graph Convolutional Network for Traffic Prediction</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dbgcn-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:27:59 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dbgcn-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Probabilistic Framework for Spatiotemporal Passenger Crowdedness Inference within Urban Rail Transit Network</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mtr-crowd-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:27:27 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mtr-crowd-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MM-DAG: Multi-task DAG Learning for Multi-modal Data--with Application for Traffic Congestion Analysis</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mmdag-kdd23/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:28:34 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mmdag-kdd23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GESA: A General Scenario-agnostic Reinforcement Learning for Traffic Signal Control</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/gesa-tits24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:29:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/gesa-tits24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL; DL&lt;/strong&gt;: OK, this title is more buzzword-confusing. We proposed a general agent that is massively trained with various city data so that it can control different cities&amp;rsquo; traffic lights that the agent has never seen during the training.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
