<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reinforcement Learning | Bonald Ziyue LI</title>
    <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/reinforcement-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/reinforcement-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Reinforcement Learning</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 15:01:26 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/reinforcement-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>CoSLight: Co-optimizing Collaborator Selection and Decision-making to Enhance Traffic Signal Control</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/coslight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 15:01:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/coslight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What life mottos have we learned from traffic signal control? Wait! What?
Yes, we learned that &lt;strong&gt;“you are your biggest collaborator”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;“Collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”&lt;/strong&gt; from the traffic light!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every driver would have realized that the traffic patterns in different regions (residential v.s. downtown) at different hours (midday v.s. evening peak) are quite different. The same should have been true of the traffic signal coordination! In our CoSLight, we co-optimize the collaborating policy ρ (choosing which traffic light as a collaborator) and the decision-making policy π (delivering which traffic control phase for the next timeslot). It turns out to be working very, Very, VERY well: our CoSLight can choose different sets of traffic lights for collaboration at different times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we also learned life philosophies from the traffic light agents, very (ironically) deep:
(1) When we drop the traffic light itself from being its own collaborator, the performance drops 2%: “You are your biggest collaborator”.
(2) When you collaborate with me, but I don&amp;rsquo;t collaborate with you, a.k.a, not being mutually reciprocal (mathematically not being symmetric), the performance drops 300%!!!: “Collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All right, “collaboration should be mutually reciprocal”: we learned the important lesson the hard way&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>X-Light: Cross-City Traffic Signal Control Using Transformer on Transformer as Meta Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learner</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/xlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 15:00:22 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/xlight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PDiT: Interleaving Perception and Decision-making Transformers for Deep Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/pdit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 23:58:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/pdit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;: In PDiT, we proposed a Transformer-interleaving-Transformer architecture for specialized environment perception and decision-making: it is a multi-modal generalist agent for vision, language, and numerics!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DuaLight: Enhancing Traffic Signal Control by Leveraging Scenario-Specific and Scenario-Shared Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dualight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 18:30:13 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/dualight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FELight: Fairness-Aware Traffic Signal Control Via Sample-Efficient Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/felight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 14:59:50 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/felight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Large Language Model-based Agents for Large-Scale Decision-Making: An Actor-Critic Approach</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/llm-actorcritic-naacl23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 23:47:28 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/llm-actorcritic-naacl23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A General Scenario-agnostic Reinforcement Learning for Traffic Signal Control</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/gesa-tits24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:29:16 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/gesa-tits24/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
