<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Smart Mobility | Bonald Ziyue LI</title>
    <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/smart-mobility/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/smart-mobility/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Smart Mobility</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:27:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Smart Mobility</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/tags/smart-mobility/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correlated Time Series Self-Supervised Representation Learning via Spatiotemporal Bootstrapping</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/time-series-ssl-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:27:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/time-series-ssl-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Probabilistic Framework for Spatiotemporal Passenger Crowdedness Inference within Urban Rail Transit Network</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mtr-crowd-case23/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2023 00:27:27 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/mtr-crowd-case23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Machine Learning for Smart Transportation (with GaTech)</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/talk/ml-its/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 15:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/talk/ml-its/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Details:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;0-syllabus&#34;&gt;0. Syllabus:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The syllabus is available 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/open?id=10flGnmEzIsPo6YFUhUAdim5VYlW_TyNB&amp;amp;authuser=bobbyli1994%40gmail.com&amp;amp;usp=drive_fs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-lecture-one-high-dimensional-data-tensor-in-smart-transportation&#34;&gt;1. Lecture One: High-dimensional Data (Tensor) in Smart Transportation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 3:30PM-4:45PM, 30 Jan 2023 (65-70min Lecture, 5-10min Q&amp;amp;A)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Zoom (&lt;a href=&#34;https://gatech.zoom.us/j/97394420485,&#34;&gt;https://gatech.zoom.us/j/97394420485,&lt;/a&gt; Meeting ID: 973 9442 0485)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: In the first lecture, we will discuss how the high-dimensional data analytics, i.e., tensor methods, could well formulate the traffic data both spatially and temporally, and we will look at the most popular tasks in ITS: demand prediction, and travel pattern clustering. Specifically, we will discuss Tensor Decomposition, Tensor Completion for demand prediction, and Tensor Topic Models for travel pattern clustering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QyoZR-UksQM&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-lecture-two-deep-learning-in-smart-transportation&#34;&gt;2. Lecture Two: Deep Learning in Smart Transportation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 3:30PM-4:45PM, 01 Feb 2023 (65-70min Lecture, 5-10min Q&amp;amp;A)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Zoom (&lt;a href=&#34;https://gatech.zoom.us/j/97394420485,&#34;&gt;https://gatech.zoom.us/j/97394420485,&lt;/a&gt; Meeting ID: 973 9442 0485)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: In the second lecture, more deep learning related methods will be introduced. Specifically, we will discuss how Self-Supervised Learning can be leveraged to deal with static time-series data such as traffic flow. We will also discuss how Contrastive Learning could learn more robust representation for dynamic trajectory. Last but not the least, we will also leverage Deep Reinforcement Learning into traffic signal control and Deep Causal Inference into traffic congestion reasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1BFLL7JT7qM&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individualized Passenger Travel Pattern Multi-Clustering based on Graph Regularized Tensor Latent Dirichlet Allocation</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tensorlda-dami22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 19:18:44 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/tensorlda-dami22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-medal&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Award:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is awarded with &lt;strong&gt;Best Student Paper Finalist Award&lt;/strong&gt; in INFORMS 2020 Data Mining Section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the previous two works in station-wise traffic flow prediction, we realized this mass traffic analysis at a macro level neglects the research value and abundant information of individual passenger travel data. Individualized travel pattern (passenger $u$ travels from origin $o$ to destination $d$  at time $t$) is believed to have higher research value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this task is rather challenging since it is high-dimensional multi-mode Spatiotemporal big data with more 7 million passengers; Also there is multi-clustering structure along each dimension of $o, d, t$; passenger behaviors are also affected by the external environment, such as the locations and surroundings of stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we proposed a novel Graph-Regularized Tensor LDA model: firstly it represents each trip from one passenger as a 3-dimensional word $\boldsymbol{w} = (w^O, w^D, w^T)$; A passenger with several trips is perceived as a 3-dimensional document $\boldsymbol{\mathcal{W}}^{O \times D \times T}$; Generative processes in the passenger-level and trip-level will be defined along each dimension and the latent topic will be also formulated as a tensor $\boldsymbol{z} = (z^O, z^D, z^T)$; Same as last work we also observed that passengers will have similar patterns both in geographically close stations or functionally similar stations. We further propose to incorporate the graph regularizations into the tensor LDA generative process for origin and destination. We also propose the tensorised variational  expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm to estimate parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the topics along each dimension of $o, d, t$ are much more interpretable and meaningful than benchmark methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Topic Models with Graphs and Applications on Individualized Travel Patterns</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/icde2021-phdsym/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 18:20:55 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/icde2021-phdsym/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long-Short Term Spatiotemporal Tensor Prediction for Passenger Flow Profile</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/lstensor-case2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 12:01:43 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/lstensor-case2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-medal&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Award:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is awarded with &lt;strong&gt;Best Conference Paper Award&lt;/strong&gt; in 2020 IEEE 16th International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traffic flow prediction is undoubtedly an essential task for both operational team and citizens. With the collaboration the Hong Kong Metro, we realize  the task to provide the citywide prediction covering all 100 stations simultaneously is quite essential yet rather challenging, especially when the data has strong spatiotemporal correlation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observed two types of spatial correlations and two types of temporal correlations in the data. We have spot that, for spatial correlations: (S1) Geographical correlation: the passenger flow of a station is usually affected by its spatially adjacent neighbors; (S2) Contextual correlations: two stations sharing similar functionalities (business center, residential area or school, etc.) are more likely to have similar passenger flows. For temporal correlations: (T1) Daily correlation: the profile is correlated with previous days of the same week; (T2)  Weekly correlation: the profile is correlated with the same day of previous weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the metro operational team, to provide long-term (several days ahead) prediction and short-term (several hours ahead) prediction are both important. And there are little work to both consider spatiotemporal correlation and offer citywide long- and short-term prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tackle this challenge, we first formulate data as a three-dimensional tensor $\boldsymbol{\mathcal{X}}^{station \times  point \times day}$ with dimension station, day, time point, to preserve the spatiotemporal nature of the data. (1.1) For long-term prediction, we proposed a &amp;ldquo;2-step 2D-ARMA&amp;rdquo; tensor prediction model, which firstly uses tensor decomposition to get day-feature matrix $\mathbf{U}^{day}$, and then conducts 2D-ARMA prediction model on this $\mathbf{U}^{day}$, capturing the daily and weekly correlations in a better way. (1.2) Another challenge for long-term prediction is how to update prediction real-time when new data keep arriving. To tackle this, we also propose a recursive dynamic updating method. (2) For short-term prediction,  we first directly used Low Rank Tensor Completion (LRTC) method to treat the prediction horizon as missing part and to complete it. But we found an interesting phenomenon: in homogeneous stations LRTC works well, however, LRTC malfunctions in heterogeneous stations. we proposed a temporary solution for it: a &amp;ldquo;Tensor Clustering + Tensor Completion&amp;rdquo; prediction model which first clusters stations and then conducts tensor completion within each station cluster for prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our method improved the prediction results significantly: for long-term prediction, 30% higher accuracy is achieved; Recursive dynamic updating method could improve the following 3 hours prediction by around 20%. For short-term prediction, with the homogeneity of stations guaranteed, and the tensor completion within one cluster can improve the prediction by 30%&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
