<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bonald Ziyue LI</title>
    <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bonaldli.github.io/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Bonald Ziyue LI</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2020 19:18:44 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bonaldli.github.io/images/logo_hua8a87e19eb81e012a11357248f4216c8_33222_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Bonald Ziyue LI</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individualized Passenger Travel Pattern Multi-Clustering based on Tensor Latent Dirichlet Allocation</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/icde2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2020 19:18:44 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/icde2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-medal&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Award:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is awarded with &lt;strong&gt;Best Student Paper Finalist Award&lt;/strong&gt; in INFORMS 2020 Data Mining Section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the previous two works in station-wise traffic flow prediction, we realized this mass traffic analysis at a macro level neglects the research value and abundant information of individual passenger travel data. Individualized travel pattern (passenger $u$ travels from origin $o$ to destination $d$  at time $t$) is believed to have higher research value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this task is rather challenging since it is high-dimensional multi-mode Spatiotemporal big data with more 7 million passengers; Also there is multi-clustering structure along each dimension of $o, d, t$; passenger behaviors are also affected by the external environment, such as the locations and surroundings of stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we proposed a novel Graph-Regularized Tensor LDA model: firstly it represents each trip from one passenger as a 3-dimensional word $\boldsymbol{w} = (w^O, w^D, w^T)$; A passenger with several trips is perceived as a 3-dimensional document $\boldsymbol{\mathcal{W}}^{O \times D \times T}$; Generative processes in the passenger-level and trip-level will be defined along each dimension and the latent topic will be also formulated as a tensor $\boldsymbol{z} = (z^O, z^D, z^T)$; Same as last work we also observed that passengers will have similar patterns both in geographically close stations or functionally similar stations. We further propose to incorporate the graph regularizations into the tensor LDA generative process for origin and destination. We also propose the tensorised variational  expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm to estimate parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the topics along each dimension of $o, d, t$ are much more interpretable and meaningful than benchmark methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long-Short Term Spatiotemporal Tensor Prediction for Passenger Flow Profile</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/case2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 12:01:43 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/case2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-medal&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Award:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is awarded with &lt;strong&gt;Best Conference Paper Award&lt;/strong&gt; in 2020 IEEE 16th International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traffic flow prediction is undoubtedly an essential task for both operational team and citizens. With the collaboration the Hong Kong Metro, we realize  the task to provide the citywide prediction covering all 100 stations simultaneously is quite essential yet rather challenging, especially when the data has strong spatiotemporal correlation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observed two types of spatial correlations and two types of temporal correlations in the data. We have spot that, for spatial correlations: (S1) Geographical correlation: the passenger flow of a station is usually affected by its spatially adjacent neighbors; (S2) Contextual correlations: two stations sharing similar functionalities (business center, residential area or school, etc.) are more likely to have similar passenger flows. For temporal correlations: (T1) Daily correlation: the profile is correlated with previous days of the same week; (T2)  Weekly correlation: the profile is correlated with the same day of previous weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the metro operational team, to provide long-term (several days ahead) prediction and short-term (several hours ahead) prediction are both important. And there are little work to both consider spatiotemporal correlation and offer citywide long- and short-term prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tackle this challenge, we first formulate data as a three-dimensional tensor $\boldsymbol{\mathcal{X}}^{station \times  point \times day}$ with dimension station, day, time point, to preserve the spatiotemporal nature of the data. (1.1) For long-term prediction, we proposed a &amp;ldquo;2-step 2D-ARMA&amp;rdquo; tensor prediction model, which firstly uses tensor decomposition to get day-feature matrix $\mathbf{U}^{day}$, and then conducts 2D-ARMA prediction model on this $\mathbf{U}^{day}$, capturing the daily and weekly correlations in a better way. (1.2) Another challenge for long-term prediction is how to update prediction real-time when new data keep arriving. To tackle this, we also propose a recursive dynamic updating method. (2) For short-term prediction,  we first directly used Low Rank Tensor Completion (LRTC) method to treat the prediction horizon as missing part and to complete it. But we found an interesting phenomenon: in homogeneous stations LRTC works well, however, LRTC malfunctions in heterogeneous stations. we proposed a temporary solution for it: a &amp;ldquo;Tensor Clustering + Tensor Completion&amp;rdquo; prediction model which first clusters stations and then conducts tensor completion within each station cluster for prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our method improved the prediction results significantly: for long-term prediction, 30% higher accuracy is achieved; Recursive dynamic updating method could improve the following 3 hours prediction by around 20%. For short-term prediction, with the homogeneity of stations guaranteed, and the tensor completion within one cluster can improve the prediction by 30%&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor Completion for Weakly-dependent Data on Graph for Metro Passenger Flow Prediction</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/aaai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 16:32:57 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/aaai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-medal&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Award:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is awarded with &lt;strong&gt;Best Student Paper Finalist Award&lt;/strong&gt; in INFORMS 2020 Quality, Statistics, and Reliability (QSR) Section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From our last paper, we found out low-rank tensor completion tends to ill-perform in heterogeneous stations. This is because LRTC assume a low rank structure in data, i.e. low-rank property implies that data in all stations are strongly and linearly dependent. However, two spatial correlations in station dimension are observed: only stations that are geographically close or functionally similar are more likely to have same passenger flow patterns. We offered a temporary solution by conducting LRTC within each station cluster to guarantee low-rank structure. But we would also like to look for a better solution, a low-rank tensor completion method that could directly handle the data with local spatial correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore we proposed a tensor completion method for Weakly-dependent Data on Graph (WDG). We formulate the geographical correlation and functional similarity as two graphs, and introduce them as two Laplacian regularizations into LRTC, namely, into station-feature matrix $\mathbf{U}^{station}$, such that if two stations are close on the two graphs, they have similar parameters on $\mathbf{U}^{station}$. Besides, since there are those two graphs on station dimension, if any 2 stations are randomly picked, they’re less likely to be highly-dependent if they’re not connected in either of two graphs. We formulate this weak dependency as a sparse coding via $l_1$-norm, such that a station is represented with only a small amount of highly-related stations as “basis”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are the first work to provide a Low Rank Tensor Completion solution to weakly-dependent pattern on graphs. And the completion result could achieve 40% higher accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discussion of &#39;A novel approach to the analysis of spatial and functional data over complex domains&#39; </title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/discussion-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 11:52:42 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/publication/discussion-paper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Dating Hack</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/project/my-dating-hack/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 17:07:52 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/project/my-dating-hack/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JD Prediction</title>
      <link>https://bonaldli.github.io/project/jd-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 16:16:03 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bonaldli.github.io/project/jd-prediction/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
